[Music]
hey everybody it's a long weekend here
in Canada the first one of the nice
weather and this is traditionally the
weekend when people open their cottages
or get their gardens going or do a big
spring cleaning what am i doing I'm
making it asking why because I love them
and I've had so many requests to do the
ripple stitch the weave stitch the
zigzag the traditional Chevron they're
all the same thing no matter what you
call it it's this action in a blanket
and this is a chevron pattern
it's a beautiful classic simple stitch
it's all double crochet and that's what
we're gonna make today so grab your
favorite Afghan hook something like a
5.5 millimeter maybe a six maybe even a
seven some nice thick warm yarn or
something skinny and baby-sized if you
want to make it for a little person this
is just the stitch so it doesn't matter
what yarn you choose it doesn't matter
what hook you choose as long as they
match grab those things grab your
scissors grab a yarn needle and let's go
to the craft table and we're going to
get into the Revel stitch for the
Chevron stitch pattern Afghan that I'm
making today I am using worsted weight
yarn in red and white these are my
patriotic colors and in particular it's
the red heart comfort so these are two
of the really big falls they make there
are thousand grams each and it's a size
four worsted medium weight yarn so
that's the yarn that I'm using because
I'm using a thicker yarn and I want my
stitches to be nice and loose I'm using
a bigger hook so I'm using a 5.5
millimeter hook you can use a six a 6.5
or even a seven millimeter hook just
remember that the larger your hook the
bigger your stitches are going to be and
the more Lacy and drapey it's going to
be so I'm gonna stick with a 5.5
millimeter
you're going to need a pair of scissors
and a your needle and I just thought I'd
show you this yarn needle because it's
kind of cool this is a
right needle for anybody who has issues
seeing the eye of a needle
this can also deal or accommodate really
thick yarn so if you ever see these you
might want to pick them up they're
pretty cool these in particular the
brand is them the kid H a kid brand and
if I find the package I will show it to
you later
and that's all you need to get started
so let's go in order to start we need to
create a foundation chain row now this
pattern is based on multiples of
fourteen plus four stitches or four
chains to start so a multiple of 14 plus
four and because I'm making a lap again
or a lap sized throw blanket I am going
to start with a hundred and sixteen
chains so that's a multiple of 14 plus
four so one hundred and sixteen chains
for me we're going to start with a slip
knot and you can make those anyway
you're comfortable make sure it can move
around on your hook for ease and comfort
and start chaining one two three four
five six seven eight you and once you've
chained your foundation row it's a good
idea to double count all your stitches
because you want to make sure you have
the right number and once you've done
that we're going to start our pattern
we're going to begin by double
crocheting so this whole stitch pattern
is worked in the double crochet stitch
so if you can do the granny square and
the fan stitch you can definitely do the
Chevron we're going to double crochet in
the fourth chain from the hook so count
one two three and into the fourth chain
you're going to double crochet wrap your
yarn around your hook put your hook
through the chain you're going to be
working wrap your yarn around your hook
and pull up a loop you'll have three
loops on your hook wrap your yarn again
pull through the first two loops that
leaves you with two loops
wrap your yarn again and pull through
the last two loops
that's a double crochet this is
considered two double crochets into the
same stitch so the chain three at the
beginning of your rows counts as a
double crochet we're going to continue
to double crochet into the next five
chains wrap put your hook through the
stitch you want to work wrap your yarn
pull up a loop wrap your yarn pull
through two loops wrap your yarn pull
through two loops we're going to double
crochet into the first five chains after
the fourth chain from the hook and that
looks like this
there's your chain three and your first
double crochet and then there's one two
three four five double crochets after
that into the next three chains we're
going to do what's called a double
crochet three together
alright this is how you do that wrap
your yarn around your hook put your hook
through the first stitch that you're
going to work or in this case the chain
wrap your yarn and pull up a loop just
like you would if you were going to
double crochet wrap your yarn pull
through the first two sets of loops or
the first two loops I should say and
that leaves you with a set of two loops
on your hook next you're going to wrap
your yarn around your hook and instead
of pulling back through these two you're
going to put your hook through the next
stitch you want to work so this is the
second of the three stitches we're going
to work wrap your yarn pull up a loop
you've got four now wrap your yarn
around your hook pull through the first
two loops now you have three loops here
but we're not finished we're gonna wrap
our yarn around our hook put our hook
through the last the third of the three
stitches that we're putting together
pull up a loop now you have five loops
on your hook wrap your yarn pull through
the first two that leaves you with four
and you're going to treat all four of
these loops kind of like you would the
last two of a regular double crochet so
you're going to wrap your yarn and pull
back to all four and that creates three
double crochet but all together into the
next five chains we're going to double
crochet one two three four and five
alright now before I go any further
let's just lay this down and look what's
happening we've got a V happening there
is a definite chevron starting
so the first fancy little thing you do
that double crochet three together is
what creates your dip or your valley so
this is the valley double crochet three
together create a valley after you have
a double crocheted into the next five we
are going to create the mountain peak
identify the next chain in a row and
instead of double crocheting three
together we're going to put three double
crochet into that single chain so these
are regular double crochets but we're
going to put three of them into the same
stitch three double crochets into the
same stitch and into the next five
chains we're going to double crochet one
two three four and five now before I go
any further we're just gonna lay it down
here and look at that now we've got an
actual wave happening so that's the
other reason that the chevron pattern is
also called the ripple or the wave
pattern because you get a very definite
wave action happening here so to recap
when you double crochet three stitches
together you get a valley when you
double crochet three stitches into the
same stitch you get a peek valley peak
this is the base of the entire pattern
so because we've done a peak and we've
put in five double crochet now it's time
to do another valley and how do we do
that we double crochet 3 together so you
identify the first chain you're going to
start your double crochet 3 together in
to work the first half of the stitch
wrap your yarn pick up the next chain
you're gonna work pull up a loop wrap
your yarn and work the first half of
that stitch wrap your yarn around your
hook identify the next chain you're
gonna work pull up a loop and work the
first half of that stitch and that
leaves you with 4 chains or the back
half of 3 double crochets on your chain
or on your hook and you're going to
treat them all as 1 this is where the
double crochet 3 together happens we're
going to wrap our yarn around our hook
and pull them all together and there is
double crochet 3 together and that
creates a valley double crochet into the
next 5 one and since we did a valley
last it's time to put in another peak we
identify the next chain in our stitch
chain this is great long next chain or
the next stitch and you're going to work
three double crochet into that single
chain or that single stitch one two and
three we're gonna work double crochets
into the next five chains one and let's
recap
definite wave action I feel like going
to the beach this is the Chevron the
pattern is now quite obvious and we're
not even finished the foundation row so
if you're excited that's a good thing
guess I'm awfully excited the last thing
we did was a peak so now we have to put
in a valley and the valley is 3
double-crochet together so we're gonna
double crochet this stitch and this
stitch and this stitch all together now
we're going to double crochet into the
next 5 1 2 3 4 & 5 we did a valley last
so it's time to make another peak so
into the next chain or the next stitch
you're going to double crochet 3 times 1
2 & 3 double crochet into the next 5 the
last thing we did was a peak so now we
have to put in a valley so we double
crochet 3 chains together or three
stitches depending on what part of the
pattern you're on this is just the
foundation row so that's why I say
chains and not necessarily stitches even
though they are technically stitches
this is the pattern that you are going
to repeat right across to the very end
of your foundation chain and when we get
there
I'll show you how to end the row just
coming up on the end of my foundation
row so I'm putting in my last 5 double
crochets
and that is going to take me up to the
very last chain in my foundation row so
I have one chain left and into this last
chain I'm going to double crochet - why
- do you ask well I'll tell you to
double crochet here counts as a half a
mountain peak so your ripple is going to
end peak Valley half a peak because it's
started half a peak Valley peak so every
single row is going to start with a half
a peak and the first combination is
going to be a full valley every row is
going to end twisted every row is going
to end with a full peak a full Valley
and half a peak and that is what your
foundation row should look like now if
you used a bigger hook or fluffier yarn
it's gonna look a little different than
mine but that definite ripple or wave
action or chevron is definitely obvious
now so now it's time to turn the corner
and work on Row two because we're
working a double crochet we need a three
turning chain so we go one two three
chains flip our work and by the time
this gets into an Afghan size flipping
is going to require lots of muscle
especially we were using big fluffy
heavy yarn because we need to start our
row with a half a mountain peak and our
chain three counts as a double crochet
we need to put one more double crochet
into that first stitch so we wrap our
yarn pick up a loop wrap and go through
the first two loops wrap and go through
the second two loops there's our half a
mountain peak we're going to single
crochet into the next five one and five
and that brings us to the beginning of
the valley we need to double crochet the
three stitches
together that make up the valley and
this is no different than working into
the chains you're just working into the
whole stitch do you wrap your yarn
pickup and work the first half of a
double crochet pickup and work the
second half the first half of the second
double crochet and pickup and work but
let the first half of the last double
crochet you'll now have four loops on
your hook wrap and finish it off all
together there's your double crochet 3
together and it continues the valley so
the pattern is the exact same for every
single row you work the next 5 double
crochet nice and normal and that brings
you up to the top of your mountain peak
and what do we do in the top of the
mountain peak we do three double
crochets all into the same stitch one
two and three here we go we're now on
row two
we started with a chain three flipped
our work and double crocheted again into
the first stitch because we need a half
a peak to begin with went five stitches
down double crocheted three together to
create the valley went five stitches
back uphill and put a new mountain peak
in three double crochet in the same
stitch now we're going to work five
double crochet downhill double crochet 3
together to create the valley work five
double crochet uphill put three double
crochet into the center or the top of
that mountain peak to create another
peak and we're going to work five three
together five three into the same stitch
five three together five three into the
same stitch and that pattern repeats and
repeats and repeats and if you're going
to make nice big wide stripes like I am
then I'm going to put in maybe four rows
of this pretty red maybe five I'll
decide when I get there and then I'm
going to show you how to simply change
yarn color and head into the next stripe
your pattern doesn't change but you can
change color anytime you want you can
make your stripes one row wide or four
rows wide or ten rows wide and just
remember to work the whole row and then
change your color at the end but when I
get to changing colors I'll show you
what I'm talking about
I'm just coming up on the end of my
second row here five and I wanted to
remind you that your chain three counts
as a double crochet and your beginning
and end of every row has to begin and
end with two double crochet in the same
stitch so when you get to the end
identify the top of that chain three and
work two double crochet into it one two
two double crochet counts is a half a
peak and you want to end with a full
Valley and a half a peak you want to
chain three to start the next row flip
your work your chain three counts as a
double crochet work another double
crochet into that same stitch because
you want to start with a half a peak and
then continue your pattern of five down
three together five up three into the
same stitch five down three together
five up three into the same stitch all
the way across and remember when you get
to the end you identify that chain three
from the beginning of the last row pick
the top of it and work two double
crochet into it I'm going to work on my
nice fat stripes now and I will see you
when it's time to change color too all
right my stripes are going to be one two
three
or five so one two three four five rows
wide I have a downhill and an uphill
count of five stitches my roads are
gonna be five rows wide and if you know
me you know how much I love numbers in
math and everything meshing together
neatly so that's what I'm doing my rows
my waves are going to be five rows deep
so now it's time for me to change color
I got to the very end of my row I
finished with my two double crochet in
the same stitch or the top of the chain
3 from the previous row and now I'm
going to cut my yarn grab my scissors
skip my yarn and just pull it back
through the working loop all the way
give it a nice tug and that's not it off
I'm going to flip my work and now you
can do one of two things here you can
grab your yarn needle and thread your
tail in as you work before you put on
the next row or you can do what I'm
going to do and that's just work over
top of it so now I'm changing colors I'm
going to start with a slipknot and I'm
going to join this in the very end end
stitch here the last stitch this would
normally be where I just chained three
to continue but instead I'm going to put
my hook in I'm going to join with a slip
stitch so that means I'm just going to
wrap my yarn around my hook and pull it
back through the working stitch and back
through the loop on my hook so that's a
slip stitch I'm going to chain three
because I'm beginning the row just like
I never change colors and continue put a
double crochet in that first stitch and
I'm going to work over top of my tails
I'm going to continue the pattern of
double crochet into the next five
stitches all the while working over top
of my tails I just find this is kind of
a handy quick neat way to do it if your
tails are long this will work out and
they probably won't unravel especially
if you go too
wash your Afghan if you are washing
Afghans wool yeah it's better to hand
wash it and let it hang dry if you're
using acrylic like I am just put it on a
very light cycle in the washing machine
and let it hang dry and it'll be just
fine so there's my chain three to begin
with double crochet in the same and
stitch five double crochet and of course
my first full exciting through the
stitch is a double crochet three
together because I'm creating a valley
and I'm just going to continue with my
new color work five rows of my new color
and then I'm going to switch back to the
other color because I'm going to own
eight between red and white nice and
Canadian patriotic but you know what for
all my American friends out there this
and red white and blue would be
absolutely gorgeous so here I go I'm
gonna continue and I'm going to make
this as long as I have yarn for
yeah so remember what I said about
making a laugh gam well I changed my
mind I like this so much I'm just gonna
keep going I'm gonna make it as long as
I want and I think I'm even gonna change
up the pattern so that I have different
colored wave stitches going oh no I
might keep the red and white I'm not
sure that's the beauty about this
pattern you can just keep going and
going and going so I'm gonna keep going
orders I love borders you know I'm
always saying that a good borders like a
frame for your artwork because of this
kind of stitch if you're going to put a
border on it you should probably just
stick to the single crochet and I talked
about this kind of border a lot in my
videos all you would do is finish your
regular pattern and when you're ready to
put on your border pick your color use
the same size yarn and the same sized
hook and just single crochet across the
top keeping the same pattern so if it's
a mountain peak you want to make sure
you do three single crochet in the same
stitch and if it's a valley you want to
make sure you do three single crochet
together in the valley you don't have to
do that if you decide you get all the
way to the end and you don't want to put
a border on it you can totally leave the
border off but if you are gonna do the
border just remember that it's a single
crochet chain two single crochet in the
corner and then when you're working up
the side you want to work a nice even
number of single crochets into this raw
edge these aren't real stitches so you
have to kind of pretend and create a
stitch as you go and a nice rule of
thumb is maybe two and a half single
crochet for each double crochet and that
will eventually work itself out when you
get up to the other end if you want to
put a border on but you don't have to
this is the chevron the ripple stitch
the zigzag the wave pattern I love it
and it is so pretty and it will be an
absolute deck or to whatever room you
want to put it in it's great for baby
blankets it's great for Afghans is great
for
it's great for whatever you want to use
it on it's a lovely simple stitch and I
hope you guys enjoyed making it with me
one more thing the last video we did was
that cute little moss stitch tea towel
holder kind of a helpful thing for in
the kitchen and elsewhere in the house
but I thought it would be such a fun
thing to make an actual dish cloth so
that is the the Moss stitch in a dish
cloth I just put a simple little single
crochet border on it anyway that pattern
for the dish cloth is available for free
up on our website so if you want to hop
on over to our website and I'm gonna
have the website rule in here so that
you can see what it looks like you can
go there go to our workshop page scroll
down the workshop page and you'll see a
picture of the Moss stitch dish towel or
dish rag and you can print off that
pattern for free and give it a try this
is a really cool stitch it's one of my
favorites and it's a good one to have in
your repertoire so since we're all about
stitches and patterns today I thought
I'd mentioned that too that's it for
today everybody I'm going to keep
working on my Afghan all long weekend
and when I'm finished I'm going to post
a picture of it up on Facebook and
probably Google+ and probably Instagram
because I can tell it's one of those
things I'm gonna be really proud of what
I'm done so stay tuned for that and if
you haven't already joined us on
Facebook in the Facebook community at
Jayden stitches please do so because we
have an awful lot of fun there and
everybody shares their pictures and it's
it's beautiful it's like this mobile
gallery I love it anyway that's it for
today everyone thank you so much have a
wonderful long weekend if you're
celebrating and if you're not enjoy the
time and the warm weather and your new
crochet stitch and we will see you again
really soon bye
[Music]
you